Guide to the Parker Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Parker Family Papers
1747-1930
1789-1866
MS 685
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(3 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, poems, estate papers, notebooks, account books, logbooks, legal books, and miscellaneous papers of the Lay, Parker, Pratt, Shaler, Smith, Stark, Tyler, and Williams families of eastern Connecticut.
Parker family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Whitlock's in 1941-1944; in part by gift of Carroll A. Means in 1941.
Scope and Contents
The Parker Family Papers consist of letters, legal and financial records, and miscellaneous items of the Parker, Lay, and other families with roots in eastern coastal Connecticut in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. The Parker family represented here is that of Gideon Parker of Essex and his children, principally his sons John L. and Gideon M., who were engaged in trade in Essex and in Key West, Florida, and Mobile, Alabama. The Parker papers are mainly commercial records and family correspondence. The Lay family papers consist of deeds and miscellaneous items belonging to members of several generations of the Lay and allied families of Saybrook, Westbrook, and Guilford, Connecticut. The Stark family is represented by correspondence of two households: Benjamin Stark of New London, San Francisco, and Portland, Oregon; and Jonathan Stark and his children of Portersville in Groton. There are also commercial papers of Nathan Tyler, B[enoni?] Southworth, and two men named Timothy Shaler; several manuscript poems, including a striking denunciation of "British Taxation in North America" signed by Lucy D. Geer of Groton; and letters by William S. Williams of Michigan and Mary Avery Smith (later Mrs. Rowland Sears) of Petersburg and Albany, New York, to their relatives in Connecticut and New York.
The Parker Family Papers were purchased from Whitlock's in several lots between 1941 and 1944, except that the photostats of the Benjamin Stark letters were made by courtesy of Carroll A. Means at the time of sale of the original letters at the Collector's Shop in 1941.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Business; Families; Shipping; Connecticut -- Social life and customs; Connecticut; Essex (Conn.); Groton (Conn.); Saybrook (Conn.); Southern States; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; West (U.S.); Westbrook (Conn.); Account books; Logbooks; Poems; Merchants; Geer, Lucy D.; Lay, Asa, 1840-1914; Parker, Gideon Marsena, ca. 1812-1874; Parker, John L.; Sears, Mary Avery Smith; Shaler, Timothy; Southworth, Benoni; Stark, Benjamin, 1820-1898; Stark, Russell; Stark, William; Tyler, Frances B.; Tyler, Nathan; Tyler, William S.; Williams, William S., d. 1834; Leet family; Parker family; America (Ship); Edwina (Ship); Lark (Ship); Severn (Ship)
- Inventory, 1747-1930; 1789-1866; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - Lay family
    - DeWolf, Lucy Rebecca (Lay) Rawson, of Westbrook, Conn., and Green River, Vt.
      - 2 ALS to her son, Edward Lay Rawson, 1866, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 2 ALS to her sister, Emmie Elizabeth Lay, 1878, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dupee, James A., of Boston: ALS to Annie L. Prince, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hayden, Jerusha, of the Wallingford Union Academy: poem, "On the death of Alfred Lay", 1810 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Holcomb, Medad (d. 1858) of Guilford: estate papers, 1859-1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Kimball, W.A. with the U.S. Army in Centreville, Va.; 2 ALS to his family (copies), 1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lay, Alfred French (1794-1810): two school notebooks, [pre-1810] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lay, Asa (1749-1814) of Saybrook: estate papers, 1798, 1811-1821, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lay, Asa (1749-1814): Captain Asa Lay of the War for Independence, by Mary Hewitt Mitchell, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lay, Edward Bliss (1792-[1864-1865]) of Westbrook: will (copy) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lay, Emmie Elizabeth (1828-1903)
      - ALS to her brother-in-law and sister, John S. Starr and Lydia Austin (Lay) Starr, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - AL (incomplete) from an unidentified correspondent of Westbrook, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lay, Jonathan W. (1825-1893) of Georgia, Vt.: ALS to his brother-in-law and sister, John S. Starr and Lydia Austin (Lay) Starr of Guilford, Conn., 1848 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Lay, Lucy White (1797-1884):
      - Commonplace book (Saybrook), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Will (Westbrook; copy), 1872 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lay, Martha (Wright) (Mrs. Steuben) of Norwich Conn.: ALS to her brother, David Wright of Boston, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lay, Richard W., of Guilford: ALS to his uncle, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lay, Robert, of Saybrook: agreement between his son and executor, Samuel Lay, and his son-in-law and daughter, Jabez and Dorotha (Lay) Denison, all of Saybrook, 1744 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lay, Samuel, of Saybrook: account book, later used as a scrapbook for clippings, 1791-1818 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Lay, Sarah (Wolcott) (1752-1840) of Saybrook: estate papers, 1837, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lay, Steuben (1787-1869) of Westbrook: estate papers, 1859, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Leete, Charles Frederic (1820-)
      - Insurance policies, 1889, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - List of Leete and Hubbard deaths, 1812-1898 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Invitation to a reception given by Orville H. Platt, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - "List of Charles F. Leets house", undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Rawson, Edward Lay (1858-): 4 ALS to members of his family, 1870-1891 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Rawson, Grindal (1803-1869): ALS to his son (Edward D. Rawson?) and daughter, 185(4?) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Stone, Joseph F., of New York: ALS to his uncle, Abram S. Fowler of Guilford, Conn., 1850 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Wright, Charles Townsend, visiting at Marion Courthouse, S.C.: power of attorney to Mary H. Wright of Norwich, Conn., 1831 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Guilford deeds, 1845-1873, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Saybrook deeds, 1783-1837 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Westbrook deeds, 1831-1876 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Parker family
    - Parker, Gideon Marsena, ([1812?]-1874)
      - Account books, 1831-1837 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Letter press book, 1836-1837 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Parker, John L.
      - Log book for the ships Edwina and Severn, 1840 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Memorandum books, 1839, 1853-1857 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Account book, 1842-1847 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Parker, Rebecca E. (Shaler or Lay?) (Mrs. John): account book with entries covered by a newspaper account of the American Congress of Churches, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1840-1866 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Pratt family
    - Latimer, Arvilla (Pratt): recipe book, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Pratt, Sarah E., of Essex, Conn.: composition book, 1863, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Shaler, Timothy, of (East) Haddam, Conn.
    - Safe-conduct pass for the schooner George, 1806 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Letter, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Account book, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Smith family
    - Sears, Mary Avery (Smith) (Mrs. Rowland Sears, 1794-1878) of Petersburg and Albany, N.Y.: letters to her sister, Clarinda (Smith) Frink (Mrs. Adam Frink, 1786-1858) of Russia, N.Y., 1816-1827 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Southworth, B[enoni, Jr.?], of (East) Haddam, Conn.
    - Accounts with members of the Shaler family for the sloop and schooner America, 1840-1843 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Letter, 1852 (Box 3)
  - Stark, Benjamin (1820-1898) of San Francisco and Portland, Ore.: incoming business letters; letters to his mother, Mrs. Benjamin Stark, and brother, William W. Stark of New London, Conn. (photostats), 1849-1852 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Stark family of Portersville, Groton, Conn.
    - Letters to Jonathan Stark from his brother-in-law, William A. Reed, and nephew, Isaac C. Reed of Goshen, Conn., and Ill., and his brother Lathrop of Bozrah, Conn.; letters to and from Jonathan Stark's sons, Russell, sailing out of Savannah, and William, sailing in the brig Emeline, 1825, 1838-1848, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Tyler, Frances R., of Boston and Essex, Conn.: diary and account book, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Tyler, William S.: account book, 1845-1848 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Tyler, Nathan
    - Bound volume containing a log of the sloop Lark, miscellaneous maritime notations, and a poem, "The Old Maid's Petition", 1789-1900 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Papers re: British compensation for the confiscation of the sloop Lark, 1798-1803 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Williams, William S. (d. 1834) and Emily W. (Mrs. W.S.) of Detroit and Pontiac, Michigan: letters to his brother, Joseph S. Williams, and his mother, Thankful Williams, of Mystic Bridge, Conn., 183[1?]-1835 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Poems
    - Geer, Lucy D., of Groton, Conn.: "British Taxation in North America" (manuscript), [ca. 1765?] (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "James Bird," re: the Kingston Volunteers in the Lake Erie campaign (manuscript), undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "Sword Presentation, at Middletown, Oct. 7th, 1862" (printed), undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "Poetry Poetry: Fire in New York; Fishermans Girl; Crazy Jane" (manuscript), undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Cold Water Army Pledge" (printed), undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - New Haven (city): At a City Meeting Holden in New-Haven, April 22, 1806. A Bye-Law for establishing and regulating a Market... (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1744-1906 (Box 3, Folder 45)